Norman Hapgood and Elizabeth Reynolds Hapgood Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Norman Hapgood and Elizabeth Reynolds Hapgood Papers 1824-1977
MSS57141
Hapgood, Norman, 1868-1937
8,000 items
26 containers
10.4 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Norman Hapgood, editor, diplomat, and author; and Elizabeth Reynolds Hapgood, editor and translator. Correspondence, family papers, speeches and writings, subject files, clippings, and miscellaneous material of the Hapgoods relating primarily to family matters, current affairs, and politics.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Baker, Newton Diehl, 1871-1937--Correspondence.; Brandeis, Louis Dembitz, 1856-1941--Correspondence.; Hapgood family.; Hapgood, Elizabeth Reynolds. Norman Hapgood and Elizabeth Reynolds Hapgood papers. 1824-1977.; Hapgood, Norman, 1868-1937.; House, Edward Mandell, 1858-1938--Correspondence.; Masaryk, T. G. (Tomáš Garrigue), 1850-1937--Correspondence.; McAdoo, W. G. (William Gibbs), 1863-1941--Correspondence.; Peabody, George Foster, 1852-1938--Correspondence.; Polk, Frank L. (Frank Lyon), 1871-1943--Correspondence.; Reynolds family.; Reynolds, Margaret T.--Correspondence.
Organizations
Columbia Conserve Company.; Germany. Heer.
Subjects
Canneries--Indiana--Indianapolis.; Diplomatic and consular service, American--Denmark.
Places
Denmark--Foreign relations--United States.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; United States--Foreign relations--Denmark.; United States--History--1865-; United States--Politics and government--1865-1900.; United States--Politics and government--1901-1953.
Occupations
Authors.; Diplomats.; Editors.; Translators.
Provenance
The papers of Norman Hapgood, editor, diplomat, and author, and his wife, Elizabeth Reynolds Hapgood, editor and translator, and their families were given to the Library by their daughter, Elizabeth Hapgood, in 1976. Additional items were given in 1978 and 1984.
Transfers
Photographs have been transferred to the Library's Prints and Photographs Division where they are identified as part of the Norman Hapgood and Elizabeth Reynolds Hapgood Papers.
Other Repositories
There is additional material relating to Norman Hapgood at Yale University, New Haven, Conn., which is the repository for the Hutchins and Neith Boyce Hapgood Papers. Theater-related papers of Elizabeth Reynolds Hapgood are in the Museum and Library of the Performing Arts (Theater Museum) in New York, N.Y.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Norman Hapgood and Elizabeth Reynolds Hapgood are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Norman Hapgood
Date Event
1868, Mar. 28 Born, Chicago, Ill.
1890 A.B., Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
1893 A.M., LL.B., Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
1896 Married Emilie Bigelow
1987 1902 Drama critic, New York Commercial Advertiser and Bookman
1903 1912 Editor, Collier's Weekly
1913 1916 Editor, Harper's Weekly
1916 Married Elizabeth Reynolds Chairman, Woodrow Wilson Independent League
1917 Foreign correspondent for a number of American papers, Europe
1918 1919 President, American League of Nations Association
1919 Appointed American Minister to Denmark
1923 1925 Editor, Hearst's International
1927 1930 Resided in Washington, D.C., working on various books, including his autobiography, The Changing Years. New York: Farrar & Rinehart, 1930
1936 1937 Editor, Christian Register
1937, Apr. 29 Died, New York, N.Y.
Elizabeth Reynolds Hapgood
Date Event
1894 Born, New York, N.Y.
1914 Graduated, Ecole des Langues Orientales, University of Paris, Paris, France
1915 Appointed head, Russian Department, Columbia University, New York, N.Y.
1916 Married Norman Hapgood
1918 Established, Russian Department, Dartmouth College, Hanover, N.Y.
1974 Died, New York, N.Y.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Norman Hapgood (1868-1937) and Elizabeth Reynolds Hapgood (1894-1974), span the period 1824-1977. The collection is organized into the following series: Family Papers, Special Correspondence, General Correspondence, Subject File, Speeches and Writings File, Miscellany, and Addition. Some of the letters to Elizabeth Hapgood are written in Russian, German, and French.
Correspondence comprises the bulk of the papers. Early letters from Norman and Elizabeth Hapgood to members of their family, as well as letters between various members of the Hapgood and Reynolds families, make up the correspondence in the Family Papers. This correspondence is dated from 1824 to 1974. There is also a considerable amount of correspondence between Elizabeth and her mother, Margaret T. Reynolds, before and during her marriage to Norman Hapgood.
Elizabeth Hapgood was a well known translator, and especially fluent in Russian. The Special Correspondence includes letters to her from friends in Africa, Europe, Russia, and the United States. The Special Correspondence also contain letters to Norman Hapgood from Newton Diehl Baker, Louis Dembitz Brandeis, Edward Mandell House, T. G. Masaryk, William Gibbs McAdoo, George Foster Peabody, Frank L. Polk, and the White House. Norman Hapgood's correspondence dates from 1896 to 1937 and relates to politics and contemporary affairs.
The Subject File contains copies of diplomatic dispatches from April to December 1919, as well as miscellaneous material concerning Hapgood's service as United States minister to Denmark. The Speeches and Writings File and the Miscellany series include galley proofs of Hapgood's magazine and newspaper articles, 1917-1918; reprints and typescripts of speeches by members of the Hapgood family and others; clippings; and printed matter and miscellaneous documents. The final series, Addition, consists chiefly of personal and general correspondence of Norman Hapgood and Elizabeth Reynolds Hapgood.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in seven series:
Family Papers, 1824-1974
Special Correspondence, 1896-1977
General Correspondence, 1866-1973
Subject File, 1901-1955
Speeches and Writings File, 1898-1937
Miscellany, 1850-1968
Addition, 1915-1937
Container List
- Family Papers, 1824-1974 (Box 1-6)
  Correspondence, legal documents, and miscellaneous papers of the Hapgood and Reynolds families. Also correspondence and miscellaneous papers relating to the Columbia Conserve Company, a family business.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of family member and therein by name of correspondent or chronologically. Material relating to the Columbia Conserve Company is filed at the end of the series.
  - Hapgood, Elizabeth Reynolds, correspondence (Box 1)
    - Hapgood, Charles H., 1937-1971 (Box 1)
    - Hapgood, David Ten Eyck, 1949-1950, undated (Box 1)
    - Hapgood, Donovan and Barta, 1961 (Box 1)
    - Hapgood, Fannie Powers, 1916-1921, undated (Box 1)
    - Hapgood, Hutchins and Neith (Box 1)
    - Hapgood, Norman, Jr., and Ruth K., 1937-1970, undated (Box 1)
    - Hapgood, William P. and Eleanor, 1917-1959, undated (Box 1)
    - Phinney, Mary Allen (Box 1)
    - Reynolds, Edwin L., 1909-1914, undated (Box 1)
    - Reynolds, Helen and Wallace, 1911-1958, undated (Box 1)
    - Reynolds, Margaret T. (Box 1)
      - 1916-1938 (Box 1)
      - Undated, (1 folder); (3 folders) (Box 1, Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Condolence on death of, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Hapgood, Emilie B. (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1909-1910 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence concerning death of, 1930 (Box 2)
  - Hapgood, Fannie Powers, family correspondence, 1838-1879, 1914-1915 (Box 2)
  - Hapgood, Norman, correspondence (Box 2)
    - Hapgood, Emma F., 1879-1931, undated (Box 2)
    - Hapgood, Charles H. and Fanny P., 1914-1920, undated (Box 2)
    - Hapgood, Hutchins and Neith, 1917-1931, undated (Box 3)
    - Hapgood, Ruth, 1890 (Box 3)
    - Tyng, Ruth Hapgood, 1889-1930, undated (Box 3)
    - Tyng, Sewell T., 1918-1931, undated (Box 3)
    - Condolences on death of, 1937 (Box 3)
      - A-W, (2 folders) (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Phinney, Mary Allen, correspondence with Beatrice Underwood (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Hapgood family correspondence, 1824-1960 (Box 3)
  - Hapgood family, wills, 1902-1945 (Box 3)
  - Reynolds, Margaret T. (Box 4)
    - Reynolds, Edwin Lewis, 1905-1917, undated (Box 4)
    - Hapgood, Elizabeth Reynolds (Box 4)
      - 1910-1940 (Box 4)
      - Undated, (3 folders); (2 folders) (Box 4, Box 5)
    - Reynolds, Wallace and Helen, 1911-1926, undated (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous family correspondence (Box 5)
  - Reynolds, Ten Eyck, correspondence with Edwin Lewis Reynolds, 1904 (Box 5)
  - Reynolds, Wallace, correspondence with Edwin Lewis Reynolds, 1910-1914 (Box 5)
  - Dolan, Marguerite C., correspondence, 1883-1916, undated (Box 5)
  - Reynolds family, condolences on death of members of, 1905-1955, undated (Box 5)
  - Columbia Conserve Co. (Box 6)
    - Correspondence, 1919-1945, (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous, 1919-1952 (Box 6)
- Special Correspondence, 1896-1977 (Box 6-9)
  Letters to Elizabeth Reynolds Hapgood from friends in the German army and from Russia before and during the Bolshevik Revolution. Also correspondence of Norman Hapgood relating to political and current affairs.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - Hapgood, Elizabeth Reynolds (Box 6)
    - Blackwall, Elsa, 1949-1970 (Box 6)
    - Briggs, Berta (Mrs. William H.) 1945-1973, undated (Box 6)
    - Kravchenko, Victor, in Russian, 1957-1958, undated (Box 6)
    - Liebbrusch, Bruno, in German, 1909-1926, undated, (3 folders) (Box 7)
    - Logofett, Alexander, in Russian 1910-1915 (Box 7)
    - Metcalfe, Louis R. (Box 7)
      - 1910-1946 (Box 7)
      - Undated (Box 8)
    - Ragozin, Zenaide A., 1923 (Box 8)
    - Syromiatnikeoff, Sergei, 1916-1933 (Box 8)
    - Trautsch, Toni, 1911-1959 (Box 8)
    - Vogel, Jaroslav, 1914-1966 (Box 8)
    - Wood, Beatrice, 1915-1977, undated, (3 folders) (Box 8)
  - Hapgood, Norman (Box 9)
    - Baker, Newton Diehl, 1916-1932 (Box 9)
    - Baker, Ray Stannard, 1918-1932 (Box 9)
    - Brandeis, Louis Dembitz and Alice, 1896-1937 (Box 9)
    - House, Edward Mandell, 1915-1932, undated (Box 9)
    - McAdoo, William Gibbs, 1916-1927 (Box 9)
    - Masaryk, T. G., 1927-1930 (Box 9)
    - Moskowitz, Henry and Belle (Box 9)
    - Peabody, George Foster, 1932 (Box 9)
    - Polk, Frank L., 1917-1932 (Box 9)
    - White House, 1919-1936 (Box 9)
  - Reynolds, Margaret T., correspondence with Zenaide A. Ragozin, 1900-1925, undated, (2 folders) (Box 9)
- General Correspondence, 1866-1973 (Box 9-12)
  General letters and memoranda received.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of person and therein chronologically. Miscellaneous correspondence is arranged chronologically.
  - Hapgood, Elizabeth Reynolds (Box 9)
    - 1903-1915 (Box 9)
    - 1916-1973, (4 folders) (Box 10)
    - Undated, (1 folder) (Box 10, Box 11)
  - Hapgood, Norman (Box 11)
    - 1893-1927, (4 folders) (Box 11)
    - 1928-1937, undated, (3 folders) (Box 12)
  - Reynolds, Margaret T., 1903-1955, undated, (2 folders) (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous, 1866-1914 (Box 12)
  - Unidentified and fragments, undated (Box 12)
- Subject File, 1901-1955 (Box 13)
  Correspondence, miscellaneous documents, notes, and reports.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Von Dorpowski, Asta (Box 13)
    - Correspondence, 1901-1955, undated (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 13)
  - Ministry to Denmark (Box 13)
    - Correspondence, 1919, Apr.-Dec. (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 13)
- Speeches and Writings File, 1898-1937 (Box 13-14)
  Miscellaneous translations by Elizabeth Reynolds Hapgood and an interview; typescript copies of editorials and speeches by Norman Hapgood, clippings, and galley proofs of his articles; and miscellaneous family writings.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of family member and therein by type of material.
  - Hapgood, Elizabeth Reynolds, miscellaneous, 1937, undated (Box 13)
  - Hapgood, Norman (Box 13)
    - Clippings, 1898-1930, (2 folders) (Box 13)
    - Editorials, 1917-1932, undated (Box 13)
    - Galleys, articles from Europe, 1917-1918 (Box 13)
    - Speeches, undated (Box 14)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous family writings (Box 14)
- Miscellany, 1850-1968 (Box 14-15)
  Calling cards, clippings, documents, printed matter, and miscellaneous writings and speeches of persons other than the Hapgoods.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material and therein chronologically.
  - Calling cards and invitations, 1860-1926 (Box 14)
  - Clippings (Box 14)
    - About Norman Hapgood, 1858-1939, (2 folders) (Box 14)
    - Hapgood family, 1863-1960 (Box 14)
    - Miscellaneous, 1901-1968 (Box 15)
  - Documents, 1850-1925, undated (Box 15)
  - Printed matter (Box 15)
  - Scrapbook (Box 15)
  - Speeches by others (Box 15)
  - Writings by others, 1911-1954, undated (Box 15)
- Addition, 1915-1937 (Box 16-26)
  Correspondence, personal and general, of Norman Hapgood and Elizabeth Reynolds Hapgood, printed matter, and other material.
  Arranged by type of material and therein chronologically.
  - Personal correspondence (Box 16)
    - 1915-1920, (9 folders) (Box 16)
    - 1921, Jan.-Oct., (6 folders) (Box 17)
    - 1921, Nov.-1922, May, (4 folders) (Box 18)
    - 1922, June-1923, Aug., (5 folders) (Box 19)
    - 1923, Sept.-1924, Dec., (4 folders) (Box 20)
    - 1925, Jan.-1926, June, (5 folders) (Box 21)
    - 1926, Aug.-1927, June, (5 folders) (Box 22)
    - 1927, July-1929, Dec., (6 folders) (Box 23)
    - 1930, Jan.-1932 July, (8 folders) (Box 24)
    - 1933, July-1937, Mar., (7 folders) (Box 25)
    - Undated (Box 26)
  - General correspondence, 1916-1934, (9 folders) (Box 26)
  - Printed matter and miscellany (Box 26)